اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
So now, covered Baiyah Tul Aqabal Al-Uolaa(بيعة العقبه الأولى)
The first Pledge of Allegiance of Al-Aqabah(العقبه),
which were, the terms of it would called the Pledge of Allegiance of the women.
Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير), has done a outstanding work in spreading the message
and by the time the next Hajj(حَجْ) season arrived,
the narrator of the Hadith(حديث) says
there was no house in Madina that didn't have a Muslim in it.
Look at the effort of Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير).
So now the appointment to meet Rasool Allah ﷺ, in pilgrimage was approaching.
So, over 70 of the Muslims went with the pilgrims of their people.
So, the delegation that came out of Madina included Muslims and non Muslims.
And the Muslims had a secret appointment with Muhammadﷺ,
but they went out with the group that was leaving from Madina.
So there are over 70 men who are Muslim and two women.
Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك), he narrates the following story.
He says;
We were among the pilgrims of our people, some were Muslim and some were non Muslim.
And our leader and elder was Al-Baraa Bin Ma'rur(ألبرآء بن معرور)
He was the leader among the Muslims.
Ka'ab Ibn Malikرضي الله عنه said;
that Al-Baraa Bin Ma'rur(ألبرآء بن معرور) came to us, in a group of the Muslims.
And he said: I have an idea and I want to get your opinion,
I don't feel comfortable turning my back towards this building in prayer.
He was referring to Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
What was the Qibla(قبله) of the Muslims at the time?
Praying to Al-Aksaa(اَلْاَقْصَى) Jerusalem.
So, the people who are in Madina, they are facing Jerusalem, while their backs are towards Makkah.
So, Al-Baraa Bin Maroor(إلبراء بن معرور) is saying, I don't feel comfortable doing that.
And I wanted to seek your advice on whether I should pray towards Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) said, we responded by saying,
Rasool Allah ﷺ is praying towards Jerusalem and we don't want to contradict him.
Al-Baraa Bin Maroor(إلبراء بن معرور) said: I am gonna pray towards Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
And from that day on, he started pray towards Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
Now the delegation made it to Makkah,
Al-Baraa Bin Maroor رضي الله عنه, he said to Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك), he said;
My nephew let's go off to the Messenger of Allah and asked him about what I've been doing on this journey,
the disapproval I have seen in you has somewhat disturbed me.
Let's go to Rasool Allah ﷺ, if what I did was right a wrong?
Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) said: We asked the man from Makkah, where is Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, the man said: Do you know him?
Have you seen him before?
Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) said: No, we don't know him.
The man responded by saying;
Do you know Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(العباس بن عبدالمطلب), his uncle.
They said: Yes,
we used to see him, in Madina on business trips.
Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(العباس بن عبدالمطلب) used to frequent Madina, doing business, so they knew him.
The man said:
Muhammadﷺ is the man sitting next to Al-Abbas(العباس) in the mosque, you will find him there.
So, Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) said: I went with my uncle Al-Baraa Bin Maroor(إلبراء بن معرور).
We went into the Mosque, and we found Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(العباس بن عبدالمطلب), and we came and greeted them.
Muhammadﷺ said: O, Uncle, Abul Fazl(أبوالفضل), Do you know who these two men are?
The elder son of Al-Abbas(العباس), his name is Al-Fazl(الفضل).
And it was a tradition of the Arabs to give a name to the Father, the father of so and so, the eldest son.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Abul Fazl(ابوالفضل), Do you know, these two men?
Al-Abbas(العباس) said: Yes.
This is Al-Baraa Bin Maroor(البراء بن معرور), the leader of his people, and this is Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك).
Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) said:
I swear by Allah, I will never forget the next statement that Rasool Allah ﷺ made,
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Do you mean, the poet.
Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) was a poet.
So, when Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(العباس بن عبدالمطلب) introduced Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) to Muhammadﷺ
and said, this is Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Is he the poet?
Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) says, I can never forget that statement in my whole life.
Why was it such a big deal to Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك).?
Because it shows that Rasool Allah ﷺ has heard of him.
And Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) was so proud and happy
that Rasool Allah ﷺ, his leader, the man who, he meets him for the first time and has been waiting for this moment to meet him,
has heard of him, he might have even heard some of his works.
So, he was so proud and happy that Rasool Allah ﷺ has already heard of him.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
ألشاعر؟
Is he, the poet?
Al-Abbas said: Yes.
Al-Baraa Bin Maroor(إلبراء بن معرور) said;
O Messenger of Allah, I have come on this journey having been given guidance to Islam by Allah,
I had the idea of not facing my back to this building.
So, I prayed towards it,
my friends opposed me in this, causing me concern.
What do you think?
Muhammadﷺ said: You already had a Qibla(قبله), a direction for prayer,
and you should have kept it.
You should have remained praying to the Qibla(قبله), that you know.
Since then, Al-Baraa Bin Maroor(إلبراء بن معرور) changed the direction.
Now with Rasool Allah ﷺ at that time,
Rasool Allah ﷺ because he was in Makkah.
He wasn't turning his back towards Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
He was facing Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) but in the direction of Jerusalem.
But the people of Madina, Al-Baraa Bin Maroor(إلبراء بن معرور) didn't like that
and Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) when Rasool Allah ﷺ made Hijrah(هجرة),
Rasool Allah ﷺ was feeling the same feeling.
Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) said;
We then left to the pilgrimage
having made an agreement to meet the Messenger of Allah ﷺ at Al-Aqabah(ألعقبه),
in the middle of the Tashreeq(تشريق) period,
so they made an appointment to meet at a specific time.
Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) says;
We kept this as a secret, none of our people knew about it
all of the non Muslims in our group, knew nothing about our meeting with Rasool Allah ﷺ,
it was secret.
Except Abu Jabir(ابوجابر), Abdullah Bin Haraam(عبدالله بن حرام),
he was one of our leaders and seniors, we went up to him and we told him;
Abu Jabir(ابوجابر), you are one of our noble leaders,
and we would like you to give up your practices,
otherwise one day you would end up as fuel for hellfire.
Abu Jabir(ابوجابر) did accept Islam.
So, they told him about the private meeting,
and he was one of the people who attended with them.
In fact, he became one of the leaders that were appointed by Rasool Allah ﷺ within this group.
It was the time for the appointment, it was late at night.
Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) said: We were going towards Al-Aqabah(ألعقبه) in ones or two's.
They didn't want to attract the attention of the people,
if you have a group of 70 going to meet Rasool Allah ﷺ, it would turn the attention of others.
So, they were going in ones and twos, until they all gathered in Al-Aqabah(ألعقبه).
And they were all there, and then Rasool Allah ﷺ showed up.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was the only Muslim from Makkah to show up at that meeting,
and he had one person with him
and that was the only non Muslim to attend the meeting,
and who was that person?
Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(العباس بن عبدالمطلب), the uncle of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(العباس بن عبدالمطلب) was the first person to speak.
He said;
Muhammad(محمد) holds with us a position of which you are aware.
We protect him from our people, who think about him as we do.
He's respected among his people and safe in his own town.
But he is determined to join up with you.
If you think you will keep trust with him, in the invitation you have given to him,
and will protect him from his opponents, then it's up to you to accept your responsibilities.
But if you think he might deliver him over, and abandon him, after he has joined you,
then leave him right now.
He does have respect and protection among his own people and in his town.
Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(العباس بن عبدالمطلب), wanted to make sure
that this is a commitment from the side of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار),
Al-Abbas(العباس) is saying that we are going to take care of Muhammadﷺ, we are protecting him.
However, he is insisting on leaving us.
Now are you going to protect him when he leaves to you or not?
How come Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(العباس بن عبدالمطلب) was there?
I mean, why was he present even though he was a non Muslim?
What is the reason he was there.?
Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(العباس بن عبدالمطلب) was the uncle of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and even though he was a non Muslim,
but he was one of the senior members of the clan of Bannu Hashim(بنو هاشم).
And even though he was a non Muslim, but he was taking special interest
in following and monitoring the activities of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and he was one of the people, who were offering Rasool Allah ﷺ protection in Makkah,
after Abu Talib(ابوطالب) passed away.
And he wanted to make sure that his nephew will be safe when he leaves Makkah.
And that's why Rasool Allah ﷺ allowed him and included him, in this meeting,
because even though he was a non Muslim, but this is again, an issue that relates to the tribe of Bannu Hashim(بنوهاشم).
Muhammadﷺ remains as a member of this clan, and his clan have interest in his safety and security.
So, Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(العباس بن عبدالمطلب) attended as a representative of Bannu Hashim(بنوهاشم), to make sure
that their son is well protected.
Now, you might say, well,
if Al-Abbas(العباس) was offering protection, how come it's different than the time of Abu Talib(ابو طالب)?
Well, the difference is that Abu Talib(ابو طالب) had respect and power and authority over his people
that none of his brothers had.
So, the ability of Al-bbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(العباس بن عبدالمطلب) to defend Muhammadﷺ
was obviously less than the ability of Abu Talib(ابوطالب)
because of the seniority of Abu Talib(ابوطالب),
Al-Abbas(العباس) was young.
Nevertheless, they still managed to protect him for that period and they viewed it as responsibility on them.
When Al-Abbas(العباس) finished his statement.
Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار) said: We have heard, what you have to say,
Now, O Messenger of Allah, ask us what you want?
Go ahead and speak to us about what you want from us
and take for yourself and for your Lord, whatever you want.
Rasool Allah ﷺ stood up and said;
I ask you to pledge that you will defend me, as you do, your women and children.
So now, this is an upgrade, a step higher than the earlier agreement in Baiyah Tul Aqabal Al-Uolaa(بيعة العقبه الأولى),
over there it is for becoming Muslim,
so they pledge allegiance on becoming Muslim.
But now there's an additional term that was added to the contract,
and that is offering Muhammadﷺ with protection, and it's a defensive protection.
He also told them, in a different narration, you must pledge to hear and obey at times of both action and inaction,
to give whether times are hard or easy, and to advocate goodness and prohibit evil,
you must speak out for Allah and not feel any blame for supporting Allah.
You must help and defend me, if I come to you.
In the same way you helped and defend yourselves, your wives and your children.
You notice here the clarity, in the message of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
I'm not coming to you, just for you to protect me, but I'm to be your leader.
You listen to me, and you obey me.
And then he said, and you fear no one, but Allah,
I cannot make this move, if you have any fear in your hearts.
You have to be willing to commit yourselves for this mission.
Al-Baraa Bin Maroor(إلبراء بن معرور), he stood up and wanted to give Rasool Allah ﷺ Baiyah(بيعة)
and he said;
O messenger of Allah, I swear it, we are warriors from father to son over many generations.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I wanted to protect me like you protect your women and children,
Al-Baraa Bin Maroor(إلبراء بن معرور) said:
O Messenger of Allah, we are warriors, we have inherited this, from generation to generation.
And this is another thing Allah prepared Al-Aos wal Khazraj(الاوس والخزرج) with,
that they were fighters, they were strong, and they had this reputation in Arabia.
And while Al-Baraa Bin Maroor(إلبراء بن معرور) was speaking
Abul Haitham(أبو الهيثم), stood up, and he interrupted, and he said,
O Messenger of Allah, we have certain ties to others, referring to the Jews,
and if we break these, we are concerned that if God gives you victory,
you might return to your people and abandon us.
Abul Haitham(أبولهيثم), is saying that this commitment means
that we will have to, we might get into conflict with people whom we have agreements with.
So now, if in case you win, are you going to stay with us, or you going to leave us,
see we are willing to enter into this agreement for our whole life.
But are you going to stay with us or are you going to leave us.?
Rasool Allah ﷺ responded after smiling.
He said;
"If your blood be sought, our blood shall be sought
and your destruction is mine as well.
I am of you and you are of me,
I will battle those, who battle you and make peace with those,
with whom you make peace."
And Rasool Allah ﷺ kept to his agreement.
When Makkah was opened, the hometown of Rasool Allah ﷺ
he left it and he went back with the people of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار) to Madina,
And he remained there until he died.
Rasool Allah ﷺ, stayed with the people of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار), until the last moment.
In another narration, there is another interruption,
when the Ansaar(أنْصَار) started extending their hands to pledge allegiance to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
As'ad Bin Zurarah(اسعدبن زرارة), the early Muslim among them, stood up and interrupted and said;
Slowly now, he's telling his people take it easy, slow down
We only hurried here because we know that he is the Messenger of Allah,
bringing him out now, however, would be provocation to all the Arabs
and would cause you to lose your elite
and would box you in, with swords raised against you.
If you are able to withstand that, then adopt him, and it will be up to Allah to reward you.
But if you are people who have great fear for yourselves,
then leave him and make that fact plain,
that coarse would be more forgivable in Allah's sight.
He said: Do you realize what agreement we're entering in,
If we take Rasool Allah ﷺ with us, that means that we are going against the whole world
and will be boxed in, with swords surrounding us,
we might lose our elites, we might spend our money,
we might be killed.
Now we either stand up and commit.
Otherwise, if you have any fear, in your hearts pull out now, when it's not too late.
They pushed As'ad Bin Zararah(أسعد بن زراره) away and said;
We will give Pledge of Allegiance.
They said, keep away from us.
We won't renegade on this pledge, we will never deny it.
Allah-Ho-Akbar(الله اكبر) look at the commitment of Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار) and the courage that they had.
Now, when Rasool Allah ﷺ asked them, to protect him,
they said; What will we get in exchange.
We are going to offer you protection even if we lose our lives and our wealth.
What are you going to give us, this is not a one sided agreement.
We are offering you help, what will you give us in exchange.?
What did Rasool Allah ﷺ say;
He responded by telling them one word,
Al-Jannah(ألجنة),
Paradise, nothing else.
I'm not gonna give you kingdom.
I'm not promising you wealth.
I'm not going to give you a few cabinet seats or ministries in my government.
I'm not going to promise you a succession after me.
All what I can promise you is Jannah(ألجنة).
And what was their response,
They said;
رَبِح الْبَيْعْ لَا نَقِيْلُ وَلَا نَسْتَقِيْلْ
This is such a profitable deal, we will never give up.
They said: what is better than Jannah(ألجنة).
Allah Ho Akbar(الله اكبر) compare this with Bayhara Bin Faraas(بيحره بن فراس).
He said: I'm going to take this young man and eat the Arabs with him.
And then he told Rasool Allah ﷺ;
If Allah gives you victory. Will you then transfer power to us.?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
No, it's up to Allah.
He said: We don't want to have anything with you.
Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار) said, That is the best deal, Jannah(جنة).
Somehow the news reached to Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), you know it's not easy to conceal a meeting of 70 plus people,
in the crowd of Al-Hajj(حَجْ).
In one narration it states that it was Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ), who announced it to the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
But regardless of how it happened.
The news reached to the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
they investigated the matter further and they found out, it led them to the right direction,
it led them to Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار).
So, next day early in the morning, a group of leaders from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
went and visited the campgrounds of Al-Aos wal Khazraj(الاوس والخزرج).
They went to them and said: We have heard that you have met with Muhammadﷺ,
and that you have offered to take him with you and give him protection.
Now, listen people of Yasrib(يثرب), you are the last people on the face of the earth, whom we want to have a fight with.
Because Quraish(قريش) knew that Al-Aos wal Khazraj(الاوس والخزرج) were not an easy opponent.
These are fighters,
truly as it was said:
We have inherited the skills of war, generation through generation.
So, the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) were saying;
We don't want to have a fight with you.
So, what have you done.
Did you really meet with Muhammadﷺ?
The Muslims, among them, among the Al-Aos wal Khazraj(الاوس والخزرج) remained silent,
and the non believers started speaking,
they said; that never happened.
We never met with Muhammadﷺ and they were speaking the truth.
They had no idea of this secret meeting that happened.
Because only the Muslims knew about it
and they kept on refuting that and said we never met with Muhammadﷺ,
we had nothing to do with him, we wouldn't see him.
Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) said: We the Muslims were staring at each other silently and we didn't speak.
The people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) were becoming convinced.
Now, Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) said that I wanted to change the topic, I wanted to change the subject.
So, there was Al-Haris Bin Hishaam(ألحارث بن هشام), one of the leaders of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), who was present.
He was wearing some new sandals, brand new.
Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) said;
I told Abu Jabir(ابوجابر), who's one of our seniors
I told him: O Abu Jabir(ابوجابر),
being one of our leaders, you can't even afford to wear new sandals like this young man of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
I mean, what's wrong with you, you're one of our leaders and you wearing this old shoes,
while this young man of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) is wearing these brand new sandals.
Now this young man of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) was quite upset by that statement,
I mean, what are you talking about my shoes, so impressed with my shoes.
So, he took them off and threw them to Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك).
Abu Jabir(ابوجابر) said;
Take it easy Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك), you have made the young man angry, give him back his sandals.
Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) said;
No, I will not give them back to him.
This is a good omen to me, I will take his booty in war.
هَذَا فَعْلٌ حَسَنْ سَاصْلُبُه
This is a good omen, I'm gonna take off from him, spoils of war.
And that was the end of the meeting.
This meeting between Rasool Allah ﷺ and Al-Ansaar(أنْصَار),
we can fairly say that it is the most important meeting that Rasool Allah ﷺ had so far.
It was a turning point in Islam.
Finally now, Rasool Allah ﷺ has a solid base to start spreading the message from, with protection,
and freedom to go out and propagate the message of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
This is Baiyah Tul Aqabah As-Thania(بيعة العقبه الثانيه).
Few lessons, and we'll close,
Number one, Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك), He states that when we left Madina,
قَدْ صَلَّيْنَا وَ فَقَّهْنَاَ
He said; We have already learned our prayers and understood our religion.
This happened before Rasool Allah ﷺ made Hijrah(هجرة).
So, for those brothers and sisters who are delaying their learning.
Until somehow they can travel overseas and go and study with the Shuyukh(شيوخ),
or get admission to an Islamic college.
You're just finding excuses for yourself.
You need to study and learn now.
Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) said: We already learned our prayers
and we understood our religion, even though Rasool Allah ﷺ was not there yet.
It's true that, they had a teacher with them Mus'ab Bin Umair(مصعب بن عمير),
but this statement has a message in it, that we're ready, we're learning.
Don't put off your learnings study Islam, spend time to learn the religion of Allah.
Try to get the best out of the situation.
If you have a Shaikh(شيخ) to teach you, that's the best,
don't have a Shaikh(شيخ), find somebody who's more learned than you,
can't find that, take a book and study.
But don't give it up, don't put it off, because you might never get the time, when you're free to do it.
And procrastination is not an excuse,
on the day of judgment, Ibn Qayyim(ابن قيم) says; when you go through the Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an
you'll find that the majority of the screaming of the people of Hellfire in Qur'an,
is because of their procrastination, because they delayed.
They say in Qur'an, the verses the narrate their sayings: O Allah take us back to this world, so that we can believe,
O Allah take us back to this world, so that we can give.
O Allah take us back, it's too late.
So, don't put it off.
Number two,
When Rasool Allah ﷺ asked the Ansaar(أنصار), his terms of the agreement.
And they said, what will we get back.
What are we getting in an exchange.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told them: Jannah(جنة).
Dear brothers and sisters, in our Islamic work, we should be working for the sake of Jannah(جنة),
to please Allahعَزّوجَلّ .
That should be our objective, not to get fame, not to make money, not for the socializing aspect of it.
We should purify our intentions every time consistently,
and make sure that we're doing everything for the sake of Allah.
This religion needs sacrifice
and if you're waiting for an exchange, if you're waiting for a payback in this world, you might not get it.
This is a religion that demands you to give it everything.
Because you are getting in an exchange Jannah(جنة), which is more valuable than anything that you could give.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
What Allah is offering you is very expensive, what Allah is offering you is, Jannah(جنة).
We need to pay the price.
Number three, Rasool Allah ﷺ was very clear in what he's asking others in conveying the message.
Rasool Allah ﷺ made it very clear to the Ansaar(أنصار), that what you are getting into is risky,
what you're getting into is a struggle.
Rasool Allah ﷺ did not promise them wealth, did not promise them power,
Rasool Allah ﷺ told them that you need to protect me, you might be attacked.
So, we need to prepare ourselves as Muslims and realized that this is not an easy walk, it's not a walk in the park.
To establish the religion of Allah, it's a struggle and it demands a lot of sacrifice.
And we need to prepare ourselves for that.
And Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said;
اِخْشَوْشَنُوْ فَاِنَّ النِّعْمَ لَا تَدْعُوْنْ
Roughen up, because bounties might not continue forever.
Easy life might not go on for good.
So, we need to be prepared and ready.
Number four,
after the second pledge of Al-Aqabah(ألعقبه)
remember again, Rasool Allah ﷺ met with 70 plus.
And there were some others maybe that were Muslim, who didn't come.
Rasool Allah ﷺ immediately, after taking the pledge of allegiance, asked them to appoint 12 Nuqabaa(نقبآء), twelve leaders.
So, he divided them into smaller groups and appointed on them leaders.
So, this shows you that this is an organized religion.
And now since there's a group living away from the organization structure of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
Rasool Ullah wanted them to have their own organizational structure.
So, immediately divided the 70 into groups and appointed 12 leaders among them,
and these are the Nuqabaa(نقبآء), who will report back to Rasool Allah ﷺ, and who, he will give them instructions.
So, this is also another lesson to learn that we need to be organized in a manageable fashion.
Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه said;
إِنِّي أُرِيتُ دَارَ هِجْرَتِكُمْ أريد سبخة ذَاتَ نَخْلٍ بَيْنَ لَابَتَيْنِ وَهُمَا الْحَرَّتَانِ
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I was shown the land of your Hijrah(هجره),
it is a land with a lot of palm trees between two rocky tracks,
Al-Harrah(ألحرة) is a rocky volcanic track.
So, that was the beginning of the Hijrah(هجرة) towards Al-Madina.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in another Hadith(حديث).
By the way, the Hadith(حديث) that I just mentioned is in Masnad Imam Ahmad (مسند امام احمد).
There's a Hadith(حديث) in Bukhari(بخاريْ),
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
رَأَيْتُ فِي الْمَنَامِ أَنِّي أُهَاجِرُ مِنْ مَكَّةَ إِلَى أَرْضٍ بِهَا نَخْلٌ
فَذَهَبَ وَهَلِي إِلَى أَنَّهَا الْيَمَامَةُ أَوْ هَجَرُ فَإِذَا هِيَ يَثْرِبُ
Rasool Allah ﷺ says, I have seen in my dream that I am migrating from Makkah to a land rich with palm trees.
I initially thought that it is Yamamah(يمامه) or Hajar(حجر).
But then it turned out to be Yasrib(يثرب), Yasrib(يثرب) is the old name of Madina,
which was changed by Rasool Allah ﷺ
and Rasool Allah ﷺ banned, the use of the name Yasrib(يثرب).
In fact, Rasool Allah ﷺ says if anybody says Yasrib(يثرب), they should make Istaghfar(إستغفار).
Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to change the identity of this city,
Yasrib(يثرب) had a history of rivalry and warfare
Rasool Allah ﷺ now is giving it a new identity, it is Madina(مدينه) Madina-Tu-Rasool Allah(مدينةالرسول الله).
What does Madina(مدينه) mean?
It is the town of Rasool Allahﷺ.
Ummo Salamah(امّ سلمه), narrates this Hadith(حديث).
She says, we came back from Al-Habashah(الحبشه)
and my husband wanted to go, again to Al-Habashah(الحبشه)
but then he heard that Madina(مدينه) is a new land of Hijrah(هجرة), and that there's some Muslims there.
So, he decided to take his family and go to Madina.
And that was one year before Al-Aqabah(ألعقبه).
So, he was one of the earliest to go.
So, she said that he mounted me on a camel and he placed my son on my lap
and we were ready to leave Makkah.
But my family came to me and said, we're not going to allow you to go with your husband.
We're not going to allow him, to take you with him to that foreign land.
So, they pulled me away, from my husband.
When Bannu Al-Asad(بنو ألأسد) the family of Abu Salamah(ابوسلمه) saw that
they came in and said, well we're not going to allow you to take the child, so they took the child with them.
So now, you have Abu Salamah(ابوسلمه) is separated from Ummo Salamah(امّ سلمه)
and they're both separated from their son.
The family of Ummo Salamah(امّ سلمه) took Ummo Salamah(امّ سلمه),
the family of Abu Salamah(ابوسلمه) took Salamah(سلمه), the child,
and now the three were separated.
So, Abu Salamah(ابوسلمه) ended up making Hijrah(هجرة) alone.
While Ummo Salamah(امّ سلمه) and Salamah(سلمه), were separated in Makkah.
Ummo Salamah(امّ سلمه) said;
I would go out of my home every day to the valley and sit on a rock and cry, for hours.
And I would do that on a daily basis.
And that continued for about a year.
Imagine this woman, mother missing her husband, missing her child.
She said: I would go out every day in the morning and just cry.
So, then one of Bannu Mugheera(بنومغيرة), my relatives saw the condition I'm in and said to my family.
This was her uncle, he said to my family, he said,
"Aren't you having any mercy and sympathy on this woman, allow her to go and join her husband."
So, they finally agreed and they told Ummo Salamah(امّ سلمه), you are free to leave.
When the family of the husband knew that, they gave her, her son
and they said now you can join your husband.
So, Ummo Salamah(امّ سلمه) picked up her child, Salamah(سلمه) and she went to Madina.
Now she was alone had no one with her.
She mounted on a camel with her son and left towards Madina, traveling alone.
When she reached to At-Tanaeem(تنعيم), which is not far away from Makkah, few kilometers outside of Makkah.
She met with Uthman Bin Talha(عثمان بن طلحه),
when he saw her, he said, daughter of Abu Umayyah(ابواميه).
Where are you heading?
She says I'm going to Madina.
He told her, Are you having anybody accompany you?
She said: No, I'm alone.
He said, Well, I would accompany you, it's not appropriate to leave you alone in this travel.
Uthman Bin Talha(عثمان بن طلحه) was a Mushrik(مشرك), he was a non believer.
But he saw this woman, felt sympathy for her and wanted to help her out.
And he was guarding her and protecting her on this journey from between Makkah and Madina.
Ummo Salamahرضي الله عنها , she says, and I swear, I was never in the company of any Arab more honorable than him.
When we made the stop, he would make my camel kneel.
And then he would move away, until I would have dismounted.
And then he would come back and take the camel and tie it.
And then he would leave and go and sleep, under a tree far away from me.
Next day in the morning, he would bring my camel prepare the saddle.
And then he would call me to come and mount and he would leave.
And when I'm on the camel, he would come back,
and then he would guide me through this trip.
And she said, he continued doing that until, we reach to the outskirts of Madina.
And we saw Qubaa(قباء) in the distance, he pointed to Qubaa(قباء) and said,
See that village over there that's where your husband is.
And he said: Now you're on your own.
Ummo Salamah(امّ سلمه), comments and says,
I know of no other family in Islam who suffered like that of Abu Salamah(ابوسلمه).
And I swear I never had a more honorable companion than Uthman Bin Talha(عثمان بن طلحه),
she was impressed, she says that Uthman Bin Talha(عثمان بن طلحه) had so much nobility
because keep in mind the animosity between Muslims and non Muslims.
For so far, Uthman Bin Talha(عثمان بن طلحه) to go out of his way and to accompany a woman who's leaving Makkah
and that's supposed to be a no-no, you're not supposed to leave Makkah to Madina.
And he went out of his way and supported her and helped her in this honorable fashion.
She liked that, and she appreciated it.
Uthman Bin Talha(عثمان بن طلحه), would later on become Muslim.
After his most of the prominent members of his family were killed in the Battle of Uhud(أحد).
But later on, he did become Muslim, he and Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) in the same time.
Also Uthman Bin Talha(عثمان بن طلحه) is from the family, which were the keepers of the keys to Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه)
and Rasool Allah ﷺ kept the keys with them and the keys are still with them today.
The family of Bannu Abd Ad-Daar(بنو عبد ادار), they are the ones who hold the keys to Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه), until this day and time.
The next story is the story of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattabرضي الله عنه says, when we decided to make Hijrah(هجرة) to Madina.
I agreed with Ayyash Bin Abi Rabiyah(عياش بن أبي ربيعه) and Hisham Bin Aas(هشام بن العاص) to be company
and to go together to Madina.
We set an appointed time to meet at Saraf(سرف), this is an area outside of Makkah.
We said, if morning comes and any of us is missing that means the person is detained
and we should just go ahead and migrate.
Morning came and Hisham Bin Aas(هشام بن العاص) did not show up.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and Ayyash Bin Rabiyah(عياش بن ربيعه) were on their own.
They reached to Madina and this was before the Hijrah(هجرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Ullah was the last one to migrate.
They reached to Madina.
Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) was the half brother of Ayyash Bin Rabiyah(عياش بن أبي ربيعه),
so Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) and his brother Al-Haris Bin Hisham(الحارث بن هشام) went all the way to Madina
to bring back Ayyash Bin Rabiyah(عياش بن أبي ربيعه)
they went to Al-Madina and they told Ayyash(عياش), your mother has made an oath
that she will not comb her hair and she will not take shadow, until you come back.
So, she will remain in the heat under the sun of Makkah and she will not comb her hair, until you come back.
The exact statement was,
"your mother has warned that she will not allow, a comb to touch her hair, until she sees you,
nor will she shelter from the sun.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) was listening.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) told Ayyash Bin Abi Rabiyah(عياش بن أبي ربيعه)
these people want to deceive you.
They want to entice you and take you back, it's a trick.
And regarding the oath of your mother, when her hair is filled with lice, she will comb
and when she feels a severe heat of Makkah she will take shelter.
So, forget about it and don't go with them.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب), he says;
لَسْتُ بِلْ خِبْ وَالْخِبِّ يَخْدَاعْنِيْ
I'm not a man who tricks others.
Neither do, I allow anybody to trick me.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) told Ayyash Bin Rabiyah(عياش بن أبي ربيعه)
don't go with them.
Ayyash Bin Rabiyah(عياش بن أبي ربيعه) he was now feeling sorry for his mother
and Umar(عُمَر) wasn't able to convince him.
Ayyash Bin Rabiyah(عياش بن أبي ربيعه) decided that he's gonna go with them.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب), told him well, if you insist, then at least take this camel of mine with you.
This is a fast and strong camel.
If you ever feel suspicious, run away.
So, Ayyash Bin Rabiyah(عياش بن ربيعه), Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) and Al-Haris Bin Hisham(الحارث بن هشام) are now on their way back to Makkah.
Everyone has their own camel.
Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) started complaining about his camel.
What a horrible camel, it's too difficult, slow.
And then he told Ayyash Bin Abi Rabiyah(عياش بن أبي ربيعه).
Can you please switch camels just for a while.
I mean, this camel of mine is causing me trouble.
Ayyash Bin Abi Rabiyah(عياش بن أبي ربيعه), beings a nice man, he is, agreed.
So, they now stopped the camels and they had the camels kneel down.
As soon as the camel of Ayyash(عياش) reached the ground, both men attacked him and tied him up.
And they dragged him into Makkah and they enticed him and he apostated.
And the same thing has happened to Hisham Ibn Al-Aas(هشام إبن ألعآص),
the third partner who was detained in Makkah.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said;
We used to say among ourselves, the Muslims, that whoever stayed behind
and foot in and was enticed by the non believers, Allahسبحانه وتعالى will never forgive them.
That was the understanding we had.
And Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said and that was also the understanding going around among, the ones who stay behind.
They felt that they have lost hope, that's it.
You have apostated, there is no way Allah can forgive your sins.
And that was their common understanding for a while.
Until Rasool Allah ﷺ made Hijrah(هجرة) to Madina and received the revelation.
Allahسبحانه وتعالى says;
قُلْ يَا عِبَادِيَ الَّذِينَ أَسْرَفُوا عَلَىٰ أَنْفُسِهِمْ لَا تَقْنَطُوا مِنْ رَحْمَةِ اللَّهِ
إِنَّ اللَّهَ يَغْفِرُ الذُّنُوبَ جَمِيعًا ۚ
إِنَّهُ هُوَ الْغَفُورُ الرَّحِيمُ۝
وَأَنِيبُوا إِلَىٰ رَبِّكُمْ وَأَسْلِمُوا لَهُ مِنْ قَبْلِ أَنْ يَأْتِيَكُمُ الْعَذَابُ ثُمَّ لَا تُنْصَرُونَ۝
وَاتَّبِعُوا أَحْسَنَ مَا أُنْزِلَ إِلَيْكُمْ مِنْ رَبِّكُمْ مِنْ قَبْلِ أَنْ يَأْتِيَكُمُ الْعَذَابُ
مِنْ قَبْلِ أَنْ يَأْتِيَكُمُ الْعَذَابُ بَغْتَةً وَأَنْتُمْ لَا تَشْعُرُونَ۝
Say, O My servants who have harmed themselves, do not despair of God's mercy.
Allah will forgive all sins.
He is the all forgiving, the All Merciful.
Turn back to your Lord and submit to Him before punishment reaches you.
Then you shall not be helped,
follow the best that has been revealed to you from your Lord, before punishment comes suddenly to you.
And you are caught unaware.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) wrote this verse and he sent it to Hisham Ibn Al-Aas(هشام إبن ألعآص),
Hisham Ibn Al-Aas(هشام إبن ألعآص) was the one, who was detained in Makkah.
Hisham Ibn Al-Aas(هشام إبن ألعآص) said: I received that verse, and I would go up to Tuwaa(طوى)
and I would read it, and reread it and I would read it again and again and again,
for a few days I would go out in this area and just keep on reading that verse
trying to understand, why Umar(عُمَر) sent it to me? What is the meaning of this verse.?
Until I understood that this verse was revealed talking about us
and say that no matter, what you do Allah can still forgive you.
If you seek forgiveness, no matter what happened.
Even if you stayed behind, even if you were enticed by the non believers, you still have a chance you shouldn't give up.
Hisham Ibn Al-Aas(هشام إبن ألعآص) said;
I asked Allah for forgiveness, mounted my camel and went towards Al-Madina.
Two lessons to learn from this.
Number one,
the forgiveness of Allah,
Allah is all forgiving, no matter what you do, never give up.
Ask Allah to forgive you.
The greatest sin which is Shirk(شرك) if a person repents from it, and goes back to Allah, Allah will forgive it.
But one needs to ask Allah for forgiveness before the punishment comes because Allah سبحانه وتعالى says,
turn back to your Lord and submit to Him before punishment reaches you.
You need to do it before, it's too late.
Second lesson,
Beware of the non believers beware, be careful.
Ayyash Bin Abi Rabiyah(عياش بن أبي ربيعه) trusted Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل).
How can you trust such a person?
Don't let the sweet words and the nice talk of the enemies of Allah sway you.
Some of us are naive.
They hear a good comment here and there, they're nice statement that is coming from this politician or that
and they fall in the trap.
Beware somebody who has a long record of fighting Islam, their record should speak for them,
so we shouldn't be tricked.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب), this plot of Abu Jahal(ابو جَهَل) did not pass on him, he knew
and he told Ayyash Bin Abi Rabiyah(عياش بن أبي ربيعه), don't believe them.
They're lying
and your mother her head gets filled with lice, she will have to comb it.
And no one will survive in the heat of Makkah.
That's an oath that she will have to break.
So, we should be careful.
And Allahسبحانه وتعالى says;
وَاللَّهُ أَعْلَمُ بِأَعْدَائِكُمْ
Allah knows your enemies.
And he has told us who our enemies are, we shouldn't fall in the trap,
We should be careful and we should beware.